Cased Images Collection, 1849 - 1860
Cased Images Collection 1849-1860
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
1000-210
1
5
Daguerreotypes and an ambrotype make up the mid-nineteenth century cased images. Most of the images are individual head and shoulder portraits, some in composites, a few are full length portraits. Typically the individuals depicted bear a Wesleyan connection.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Special Collections & Archives staff assembled the cased images from individual donations. Individual donors, when known, are noted in listing.
Collection Overview
The collection is an assemblage of mid-nineteenth century cased portrait images, mostly daguerreotypes and an ambrotype. Most of the images are individual head and shoulder portraits. There are composite shots of Wesleyan University classes of 1849, 1850, 1852, 1853, and 1854. There are a few are full length portrait images. Typically the individuals depicted bear a Wesleyan connection. The cased images are in order of approximate date.
Collection Arrangement
The items arranged invidually by type and date.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Portraits.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Alumni and alumnae.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Ambrotypes (photographs).; Composite photographs.; Daguerreotypes (photographs).
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Class of 1849, circa 1849 (Box 1)
    Daguerreotype, 1/4 plate, 4 3/4 x 4 inch exterior
    Composite. Portrait shots of 33 men shown in 1 row of 3 and 5 columns by 6 rows
    Handwritten in inner side of case "Wesleyan University Middletown Conn Graduating Class of 1849"
    Front case cover missing
    Gift of Mrs. Robert W. Sale in 1969, great-granddaughter of John Wesley Jones, Class of 1849.
    71.161
  - Class of 1850, circa 1850 (Box 1)
    Daguerreotype, 1/2 plate, 4 3/4 x 6 inch exterior
    Composite. Portrait shots of 20 men shown in 4 columns by 5 rows
    Gift of from G. F. Steele, son of George McKendree Steele, Class of 1850.
    71.156, 01.680.4
  - Class of 1850, circa 1850 (Box 1)
    71.162
  - Class of 1852, circa 1852 (Box 1)
    Daguerreotype, whole plate, 7 x 9 inch exterior
    Composite. Portrait shots of 24 men shown in 6 columns by 4 rows
    Gift of K. P. Harrington
    71.164
  - Class of 1852, circa 1852 (Box 2)
    71.163
  - Class of 1852, circa 1852 (Box 2)
    Daguerreotype, whole plate, 7 1/4 x 9 1/4 inch exterior
    Case cover missing
    Gift of William Griffing, accession number 2002-48
  - Class of 1853, circa 1853 (Box 2)
    Daguerreotype, whole plate, 8 x 10 inch exterior
    Case missing; matted, in glass, edges secured
    Gift of Mrs. W. A. Pine, granddaughter of Franklin Hannahs, Class of 1853
  - Class of 1853, circa 1853 (Box 3)
    Page laid in: Class of 1853 - Wesleyan University [list of depicted class members]
    Gift of Christine M. Ayers in 1977, granddaughter of William W. Fairfield, Class of 1853
    71.165
  - Class of 1854, circa 1854 (Box 3)
    Hinge repaired
    71.159
  - Class of 1854, circa 1854 (Box 4)
    Front case cover detached
    Gift of Sydney T. Maunder in 1967, grandson of Joseph J. Turton, Class of 1854
    71.160
  - Class of 1854, circa 1854 (Box 4)
    71.166
  - Hamilton Brewer, Class of 1838, circa 1840-1849 (Box 5)
    Daguerreotype, 1/6 plate, 3 3/4 x 3 inch exterior
    Front cover detached
    Gift August, 1986
  - Clark Coolidge, Class of 1841, circa 1855-1865 (Box 5)
    Ambrotype, tinted, 1/6 plate, 3 3/4 x 3 1/4 inch exterior
    Print of Wesleyan College annotated "Middletown College" laid in
    Front cover of case partially detached
    Gift of Mrs. F. Loring Wheeler
    31.1
  - Laura and Lovell Hall, Class of 1866, circa 1849-1850 (Box 5)
    Daguerreotype, tinted, 1/6 plate, 3 3/4 x 3 1/4 inch exterior
    Image is notably faded, tarnishing at edges
    71.167
  - Francis S. Hoyt, Class of 1844, circa 1850-1859 (Box 5)
    Gift of Frank F. Starr
  - Albert Sanford Hunt, Class of 1851, undated (Box 5)
    Daguerreotype, 1/6 plate, 3 x 3 1/2 inch exterior
    Case cover detached
    71.169
  - Phoebe Augusta Moser and George Ingraham Seney, Class of 1845, circa 1855-1860 (Box 5)
    Daguerreotype, 1/2 plate, 6 x 4 3/4 inch exterior
    Gift of Ken Appollo, Class of 1972, in 1992
    92.13
  - Albert D. Vail, Class of 1857, circa 1850-1859 (Box 5)
    Daguerreotype, tinted, 1/4 plate, 4 3/4 x 3 3/4 inch exterior
    71.017
  - Seated man and woman, woman holding Stephen Olin's Discourse on the Resources and Duties of Christian Young Men on her lap, circa 1845-1860 (Box 5)
    Daguerreotype, 1/6 plate, 3 1/4 x 3 3/4 inch exterior
    Hinge repaired with black tape
    Gift of Thos. A. Cox, 1989
    89.3